TOPIC
    about_Scripting_ValidateCount

SHORT DESCRIPTION
    A brief tutorial on validating parameters by count
    
LONG DESCRIPTION
    Here’s another parameter validation attribute you might want to use in
    your PowerShell scripting and functions. If your parameter can take an
    array of values, you might want to limit that array to a certain size. 
    For example, your parameter can take an array of computer names but you 
    don’t want to process more than 5 for some reason. This is where 
    [ValidateCount()] comes in to play.

    This attribute takes two values, the minimum number of accepted parameter
    values and the maximum.

    [ValidateCount(1,10)]
    [string[]]$Computername
    
    If used, this would mean I would need at least one computername but no 
    more than 10. You could also set both values the same if you wanted an 
    exact number:

    [ValidateCount(2,2)]
    [int[]]$Numbers
    
    Now, I’d have to pass exactly 2 numbers as parameter values. Let’s look 
    at a more complete example.

    #requires -version 2.0

    Param (
    [Parameter(Position=0,Mandatory=$True)]
    [ValidateCount(1,5)]
    [string[]]$Name
    )

    Foreach ($item in $name) {
        #display the name in a random color
        Write-Host $item -ForegroundColor ([system.consoleColor]::GetValues(
        "system.consolecolor") | get-random)
    }
    
    This simple script writes each name in a random color, assuming I pass 
    no more than 5 names.

    If I exceed that count, PowerShell will throw a tantrum (I mean exception).

    When you use this validation test, be sure your parameter is set to 
    accept an array of values, e.g. [string[]].

SEE ALSO
    about_Functions_Advanced_Parameters
    http://jdhitsolutions.com/blog
