TOPIC
    about_Scripting_Best_Practices

SHORT DESCRIPTION
    A list of recommended scripting best practices.

LONG DESCRIPTION
    Writing a PowerShell script or function is only a little different than
    using the interactive console. If you can run a command at the console
    you can copy and paste that into your script file and vice versa. But,
    whereas the goal in the console is economy and efficiency, in scripting
    the goal is clarity and consistency.
    
    To that end, here a some recommended best practices for writing your own
    PowerShell scripts and functions.
    
    NAMING
        Wherever possible, name your scripts and functions using the accepted
        Verb-Noun format. Use one of the standard verbs that you see when
        running Get-Verb. The noun can be a bit more flexible, but try to keep
        it singular.
        
        If you think your noun might conflict with another cmdlet, then use a 
        prefix. If you are building a collection of functions or a module you
        might want to do this anyway. Instead of creating a function called
        Get-File you might call it Get-MyFile.
    
    NO ALIASES
        When calling a cmdlet in your script or function, always refer to it
        by it's full name and never an alias. It may take a moment longer to 
        write, but you only have to do it once and the full cmdlet name makes
        it easier to understand.
        
        An exception can be made for well known aliases like DIR.
        
    PARAMETERS
        On a related note, always use full parameter names, even for positional
        parameters. A command like:
        
          Get-WMIObject -class win32_operatingsystem -computername SERVER01
        
        is much easier to understand than:
        
          gwmi win32_operatingsystem -co SERVER01
        
        Yes, the command may take longer to write, but at least it will be
        clear and self-documenting.
    
    FUNCTIONS OR SCRIPTS?
        One of your first decisions is whether you are writing a standalone
        script or a function.  Of course, functions need to reside in a script
        file that you can then dot source or include in a module. My rule of
        thumb is to write functions for repeatable, modular, or atomic 
        commands that can be incorporated into the pipeline or a larger script.
        
        I use stand-alone scripts when I have a series of commands that I need
        repeated periodically but obviously don't want to type them. Or I need
        to ensure consistency. I think of these scripts as "canned" PowerShell
        sessions. In fact a great way to build this type of script is to start
        a transcript, run through your commands and then edit your transcript,
        deleting everything but your commands. The resulting script can be run
        at anytime to "recreate" the PowerShell session. Of course, you can
        include your own functions as well. Remember that functions must be
        defined before you can call them.
    
    SINGLE PURPOSE
        Especially when writing functions, keep your function focused on a
        single task. Don't write a monolithic function that does everything.
        Write a function that does one thing and that can participate in the
        pipeline. You want to maintain flexibility. For example, if you include
        code in your function to write your data to Format-Table, you can't
        do anything else with that function except send it to a cmdlet like
        Out-File. If tomorrow you decide you need to sort on the output, you
        can't. 
        
        My corollary best practice is to keep formatting separate from your
        scripts and functions.
       
    RETURN vs WRITE
        Try to avoid using the RETURN keyword at the end of your function. 
        Think "writing objects to the pipeline" and not "returning values".
        When you use RETURN, PowerShell will write the value to the pipeline
        and then terminate the pipeline. If you have more data or more 
        commands after RETURN you'll never see them.
       
    WRITE-HOST
        Do not use Write-Host to output data from your script or function. 
        This cmdlet writes to the console and not the pipeline which means 
        you can't pipe your script or function to other PowerShell cmdlets 
        such as Sort-Object or Out-File. Using Write-Host for informational
        messages is a good use. I recommend using a foreground or background
        color with Write-Host so you can differentiate your messages from the
        actual output. 
        
        You might also consider implementing Write-Verbose or Write-Progress.
        
    CODE FORMATTING
        Make your PowerShell scripts easy to read. Take advantage of whitespace
        and indentations. The worst thing you can do is create a 100 line
        script that is single spaced and left-justified. Nobody will be able
        to help you debug or troubleshoot. There are no performance penalties.
        
        You should also come up with a formatting style or template and be
        consistent. This is especially important if you are developing scripts
        in a team setting.        
    
    DOCUMENTATION
        Finally, it is very important that you document your script, especially
        sections that might be complex or involve scripting constructs like
        IF or SWITCH. The comment character is #. You can use it like this:
        
           get-service | 
             where-object {$_.status -eq 'Running'} #Get all running services
             
        Or like this, which is what I prefer:
            
            #Get all running services
            get-service | 
             where-object {$_.status -eq 'Running'} 
        
        If you have several documentation lines, then use this format:
        
            <#
                I am a long document comment.
                It is very important that you read me.
            #>
        
        I recommend that when you start developing your script or function to
        write each step or task that you want to accomplish as a comment. This
        helps you organize your thoughts and layout the script of function. 
        Then all you need to do is write code to meet the documentation and 
        when you are finished, your script is already documented.
        
SEE ALSO
    About_functions
    About_functions_advanced